Guide to the Eadweard Muybridge Photograph Collection
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Eadweard Muybridge photograph collection
1868-1929
PC0006
Muybridge, Eadweard, 1830-1904
8.25 Linear feet
This collection includes original Muybridge glass plate negatives and prints, as well as modern day copy prints of his photographs. Original materials, 1872-1880, include images of the Stanfords' residences in Sacramento and San Francisco, other unidentified estates, and two printed cards from his horse in motion series, 1878. Images represented by copy prints include Canadian Pacific Railway, Indians, San Francisco, Oakland, and several Central America photographs. Also included in the collection is a set of glass slides, primarily of images included in this collection, probably assembled by Harry C. Peterson, former curator of the Stanford Museum.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Eadweard Muybridge was born in Kingston-upon-Thames, England, in April 1830 as Edward James Muggeridge. He came to the United States in 1851 and worked for two publishing companies on the east coast until 1855, when he moved to California and established a book store in San Francisco. In 1860 he set off on an extensive journey east through the United States and on to Europe, but was injured in a stagecoach accident in Texas. He spent some time in England recuperating and back in the States suing the stage coach company, but not all of his activities between 1860 and 1866 are known.
In 1867 he returned to California and commenced his photography career, focusing for the next six years on California and the Far West. He traveled in Central America and Panama during 1875 to 1876; and in 1876 and 1877 he completed his panorama of San Francisco.
Muybridge worked closely with Senator Leland Stanford on experiments to record horses in motion, trying first to answer the question of whether or not all four feet are off the ground during the trot. In 1873 he successfully captured that event in Sacramento, using Leland Stanford's horse Occident as his subject. He made further photographs of Occident in 1877 and then in 1878-1879 he set up a studio at Stanford's Palo Alto Stock Farm and conducted many photographic experiments of horses in motion.
Description of the Collection
This collection includes original Muybridge glass plate negatives and prints, as well as modern day copy prints of his photographs. Original materials, 1872-1880, include images of the Stanfords' residences in Sacramento and San Francisco, other unidentified estates, and two printed cards from his horse in motion series, 1878. Images represented by copy prints include Canadian Pacific Railway, Indians, San Francisco, Oakland, and several Central America photographs. Also included in the collection is a set of glass slides, primarily of images included in this collection, probably assembled by Harry C. Peterson, former curator of the Stanford Museum.
Access Terms
Muybridge, Eadweard, 1830-1904; Palo Alto Stock Farm (Stanford, Calif.); Stanford, Leland, 1824-1893.; Albumen prints.; Glass plate negatives.; Palo Alto (Calif.) Stock Farm; Photonegatives; Photoprints.; Stanford residences--Sacramento.; Stanford residences--San Francisco.; Yosemite National Park (Calif.) --Photographs.
Collection Contents
- Stanfords' Sacramento residence, glass plate negatives
  - Exterior, #13601 rear view, 8749, 8759 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Exterior, #13602 front and west end view, 8752, 8756 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Exterior, #13604 west side view - 8th Street, 8751, 8758 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Exterior, #13603 north and east side view, N Street, carriage in front, 8757 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Exterior, #13599 front entrance - N Street, 8725, 8750 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Interior, #13512 hall, main stairs, 8707, 8727 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Interior, #13523 sitting room looking into music room, 8709, 8696, 8715 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Interior, #13503 sitting room looking into music room, 8710, 8716 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Interior, #13523 dining room looking west, 8721, 8740 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Interior, #13582 sitting room and dining room looking east, 8706, 8720 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Interior, #13558 sitting room looking west, 8712, 8734 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Interior, #13570 parlor looking south, 8714, 8724 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Interior, #13573 parlor looking north, 8711, 8733 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Interior, #13586 sun porch looking west, 8732, 8736 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    left to right: Jane Anne Shields Lathrop, Elizabeth Stanford, Anna Maria Lathrop, Jane Lathrop Stanford, Leland Dewitt Stanford
  - Interior, #13583 sun porch looking west, 8731, 8735 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Interior, #13571 ballroom looking east, 8730 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Interior, #13573 ballroom looking west, 8708, 8728 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Interior, #17153 billiard room, 8697, 8723, 8738 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - (left to right: Leland Dewitt Stanford, Jane Lathrop Stanford, Anna Maria Lathrop) (Box 1)
  - Interior, #135?? billiard room looking north, 8713, 8729 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Interior, #13584 billiard room looking south, 8701, 8726, 8737 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    left to right: Anna Maria Lathrop, Jane Lathrop Stanford, Leland Dewitt Stanford
  - Interior, #13553 bedroom, 8704, 8717 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Interior, #13522 bedroom, 8718, 8719 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Interior, #13521 bedroom, 8703, 8705 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Interior, #13565 bedroom "Bertha Berner's room", 8702, 8722 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Stanfords' San Franciso House, glass plate negatives
  - Construction of house [possibly not a Muybridge photo] (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Exterior, also showing Hopkins house under construction [Jane Stanford in front?] (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Exterior, also showing Hopkins house under construction [possibly not a Muybridge photo] (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Exterior, also showing Hopkins house under construction [possibly not a Muybridge photo], circa 1876; 13605 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Prints, original and copies
  - Atherton estate, original Muybridge print, pre 1872; 6425 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Bierstadt, Albert, painting in Yosemite, modern copy print, 6431 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Canadian Pacific Railway, modern copy prints
    - Bridge with workers, 6446 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Bridge and trestle with one man standing on tracks, 6447 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Bridge and trestle with one man, different view, 6448 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Rock formation along bend in tracks, 6449 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Horse in Motion
    - Mahomet cantering, 6 images on card with text on reverse, circa 1878; 6413 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Sally Gardner running, 12 images on card with text on reverse, circa 1879; 6414 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Setting up Muybridge's studio on Stanford campus, modern copy print, 6450 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Indians, modern copy prints
    - A summer campsite, 6432 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - A morning concert, 6433 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Making bread, 6435 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Modoc Indian brave, 6442 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Menlo Park, boating in (3 men in a canoe), modern copy print, 6430 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous images, modern copy prints
    - Emperor Norton (character on bicycle), 6417 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - General Jefferson Davis, posed with other soldiers, 6445 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous images, modern copy prints
    - Woodward's Garden, [San Francisco,] view of the pond, 6438 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - "Heartsease" from glass plate negative, b/w and sepia toned prints, 6416 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Oakland, CA, modern copy prints
    - Large oak in field, 6426 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Man with ax under trees, 12th Street bridge across Lake Merritt can be seen, 6427 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Boy and girl sitting under a tree, 6428 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Two women and two girls walking under trees, 6429 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - San Francisco, CA, modern copy prints
    - Montgomery St. at Market St., 6418 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Geary St. from Market St., 6419 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Ship in dry dock at Hunter's Point, 6420 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Damage from the earthquake of 1868, 6421 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - View of San Francisco harbor, 1860s; 6422 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Stanfords' San Francisco residence, 1877 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    mounted albumen print; caption is "Panorama of San Franciso from California Street Hill"
  - Stanfords' San Francisco residence, copy prints, 1985
    - Vestibule, 12839 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Library, 13539 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Blue and gold guest chamber (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - View of house [copy print of original in folder 11] (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Dining room, 13681 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - View of S.F. from the house (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Copy prints from images in the Bancroft Library collection:
    - Miscellaneous
      - S.S. Costa Rica on the rocks outside the Golden Gate, 6423 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - Yosemite Indians, 6434 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - Log rolling at Shoal Water Bay, 6439 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - New Year's Point, 6440 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - Cloister of Santa Clara University, 6441 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Panama
      - Man on beach with houses behind, 1876; 6443 (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - Road through a town, 1876; 6444 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - San Quentin
      - The hospital at San Quentin, 6436 (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - View of the wheel works, 6437 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - San Rafael orphanage
      - Exterior view, with staff and children (boys), 6424 (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - Boys in classroom, 6425 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Glass plate negatives of miscellaneous images
  - Horses, #13610 "Hank Smith and Occident," Sacramento 1872 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Horses, #13607 "Charles Wooster driving Stanford's private team," 1872 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Horses, #13608 "Charles Wooster driving Stanford's private team," 1872 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Horses, #13609, "James Vickers, Stanford's colored coachman," 1872 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - View of unknown estate, #13596 house, barn, and water tank (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - View of unknown estate, #13587 cottage, water tank, and grounds (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - View of unknown estate, #13595 oak-lined drive leading to barn (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - View of unknown estate, #13592 view from hill, overlooking wooded area (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - "Heartsease," view of horse and wagon coming through estate gate signed "Helios 1880" (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Prints of images related to Muybridge
  - Muybridge's cameras, 2 images, 6412, unnumbered (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Memorial tablet on the Quad regarding "horse in motion" photographs, post 1929; 6451 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Stanfords' San Francisco residence, mounted original prints
  - Hall, 12839 (Box 4)
  - Mosaic floor in center of rotunda, 12835 (Box 4)
  - Drawing room (Pompeian Room), 12842 (Box 4)
  - Blue and Gold guest chamber, 12845 (Box 4)
  - Mrs. Stanford's bedroom, 12844 (Box 4)
  - Mrs. Stanford's sitting room, 12843 (Box 4)
  - [Breakfast room?], 12836 (Box 4)
    note in pencil on front "All these proofs are printed too dark - Muybridge"
  - Mrs. Stanford's bedroom - note in pencil on front "Printed too dark - Muybridge" [dup of 12844], 12841 (Box 4)
  - Mrs. Stanford's sitting room, 12837 (Box 4)
  - [Ceiling murals in rotunda], 12840 (Box 4)
- Stanford's San Francisco residence, photo album
  - Page: 1 | Title: Breakfast room looking west, 13556 (Box 5)
  - Page: 2 | Title: Breakfast room looking east (Box 5)
  - Page: 3 | Title: Bay window in drawing room west side with fountain, 13524 (Box 5)
  - Page: 4 | Title: Dining room looking toward south bay window (Box 5)
  - Page: 5 | Title: Dining room looking into picture gallery, Pompeian room and hall, 13681 (Box 5)
  - Page: 6 | Title: Conservatory opening into Mrs. Stanford's sitting room, 13566 (Box 5)
  - Page: 7 | Title: Mrs. Stanford's sitting room looking toward the south (Statue of Mercury), 13515 (Box 5)
  - Page: 8 | Title: Mrs. Stanford's sitting room looking into billiard room, 13538 (Box 5)
  - Page: 9 | Title: Mrs. Stanford's sitting room looking into billiard room, Library, 13546 (Box 5)
  - Page: 10 | Title: Billiard room looking toward hall (Box 5)
  - Page: 11 | Title: Billiard room looking into library, 13527 (Box 5)
  - Page: 12 | Title: Library looking toward hall to reception room, 13535 (Box 5)
  - Page: 13 | Title: Library looking toward hall and billiard room, 13539 (Box 5)
  - Page: 14 | Title: Library looking toward bay window (Box 5)
  - Page: 15 | Title: Guest chamber, blue and gold room, 13532 (Box 5)
  - Page: 16 | Title: Mrs. Stanford's bedroom looking toward windows east side, 13525 (Box 5)
  - Page: 17 | Title: Hall looking toward the front door, statues of morning and night, 13549 (Box 5)
  - Page: 18 | Title: View of upper hall [rotunda] looking toward front, 13555 (Box 5)
  - Page: 19 | Title: View of upper hall [rotunda] looking toward back, 13530 (Box 5)
  - Page: 20 | Title: Upper hall painting of Europe over rotunda (Box 5)
  - Page: 21 | Title: Upper hall painting of Africa over rotunda, 13528 (Box 5)
  - Page: 22 | Title: Upper hall painting of Asia over rotunda, 13529 (Box 5)
  - Page: 23 | Title: Upper hall over rotunda painting of America (Box 5)
  - Page: 24 | Title: Reception or India room looking into library, 13510 (Box 5)
  - Page: 25 | Title: Reception or India room looking into library [different view than 13510] (Box 5)
  - Page: 26 | Title: Reception or India room looking toward front windows with statue of innocence, 13537 (Box 5)
  - Page: 27 | Title: Dining room looking into picture gallery, 13536 (Box 5)
  - Page: 28 | Title: Picture gallery [long side wall], 13548 (Box 5)
  - Page: 29 | Title: Picture gallery [other long side wall], 13540 (Box 5)
  - Page: 30 | Title: Picture gallery [view from one end] (Box 5)
  - Page: 31 | Title: Picture gallery [view from the other end], 13547 (Box 5)
  - Page: 32 | Title: Drawing or Pompeian room looking toward west [repeated photo number], 13532 (Box 5)
  - Page: 33 | Title: Drawing or Pompeian room, statue of the fountain of love [repeated photo number], 13532 (Box 5)
  - Page: 34 | Title: Statue of the fountain of love, Pompeian room, 13531 (Box 5)
- Copy negatives of Muybridge images
  - GP 6413, 6414 (front and back images), 6421, 6431, 6450, 6451, 8708 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Muybridge (prints) # 12835, 12842, 12845 and Muybridge (glass neg) # 13584 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Sacramento House images (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - San Francisco House, interiors (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Conservatory of the Doyle home, Menlo Park (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Negatives for some of the glass slides (see box 7) (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Negatives for images not by Muybridge:
  - San Francisco House, architects' drawings (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Ceremony at unveiling of plaque in the Quad re Muybridge and motion pictures, May 1929 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Glass slides of Muybridge images or related subjects, positive images
  - Animal Locomotion and Miscellaneous images
    - Leland Stanford (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Muybridge portrait (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Bierstadt working in Yosemite (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Earthquake damage in San Francisco, 1868 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Leland Stanford Jr. driving [one frame from a motion study] (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Collage of Central America and Mexico photos (Box 7, Folder 5a)
    - Bay of Panama (Box 7, Folder 5b)
    - Coffee pickers at their ablutions (Box 7, Folder 5c)
    - View of Stock Farm barn from hills (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Map of Stock Farm showing track, paddocks, barns (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Setting up cameras at Stock Farm (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Setting up cameras at Stock Farm, different view (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Camera and apparatus (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Camera and apparatus (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Horse jumping [motion study series] (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Remnants of Muybridge's shutter (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Leland Jr., Mrs. Stanford, and Muybridge (with 2 others) standing by camera/studio arrangement (Box 7, Folder 13a)
    - Sallie Gardner running [repro of the published card], 1878 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Reverse side of Sallie Gardner running, 1878 [repro of the published card] (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Muybridge greeting the athlete on the track (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Color repro of portrait of Leland Stanford (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Sketch of Muybridge studio set-up at Stock Farm (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Sketch of unknown machine (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Title page of Animal Locomotion (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Drawing of horses in motion (pre-Muybridge concept of motion) (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Drawing of cowboy on horse (more accurate depiction of motion) (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Original Muybridge studio as it was in 1913 [color added to grass] (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Interior of Muybridge studio, 1912 (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Occident trotting [motion study] (Box 7)
  - Stanford San Francisco House
    - Exterior view, 1878 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Ball room [Sacrmento house], 1876 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Pompeian Room (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Hall below Rotunda (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Sideboard in the dining room (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Close up of a fireplace, room not specified (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Upper rotunda, with two portraits, 1880 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Sofa in Pompeian Room (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Art Gallery, 1880 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - India Room (Box 8, Folder 10)
- The Horse in Motion, Accession ARCH.2014-056
  - The Horse in Motion: Sallie Gardner running, 12 images on card with text on bottom, 1878 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Eadweard Muybridge Yosemite photographs, 1872; Accession ARCH-2015-011
  10 albumen photographs printed from replicated negatives made from photographs by Muybridge. 17 1/4" x 21 1/2", mounted on 24 1/2" x 29 1/2" heavy archival baords. Limited edition printed by the Chicago Albumen Works, Inc. and published by Yosemite Natural History Association, 1977. Only 50 sets were produced.
  - Yosemite photographs, 1872 (Box 1)